PHILIP GREENSPUN: We're going
to talk about meteorology.
So as pilots, we're just trying
to understand the basics.
And in terms of
passing the exam,
you don't need to
be a physicist.
You just mostly
are trying to learn
stuff that will help you fly
within the VFR weather minimums
and predict when those minimums
aren't likely to be met
or when there's going to
be really serious hazards,
such as thunderstorms.
All right, this
will be on the test.
You have to memorize
all of this.
Well, you kind of do.
Anyways, they want you--
you will have to learn some
of this stuff for the exam.
In reality around here,
almost all airspace
is at least class echo.
That's controlled airspace.
It means controllers
could give you a clearance
to fly on instruments
and separate you
from other aircraft.
So they want you to be
well separated from clouds,
1,000 feet above, 500 feet
underneath, 2,000 horizontally.
That way, if an aircraft under
IFR comes out of the clouds,
there'll be some time
for the two of you
to see and avoid each other.
You can see the weather minimums
are different in class Golf
airspace.
And, actually, in
uncontrolled airspace
like up in Alaska, if you're
flying on instruments,
you don't have a clearance.
So you'll say, well,
how is that possible?
You can be instrument rated,
have an instrument capable
airplane, and fly from airport
to airport in the clouds.
But the air traffic controllers,
they can't give you a clearance
and guarantee you separation
from other aircraft
because they don't have radar.
They don't even
have the authority.
It's not controlled airspace.
I've done some flying up
there in little airplanes,
and you have to be very patient.
Another interesting thing
to notice about this--
we'll talk about it
more again later--
is notice how class
Bravo airspace
has lower minimums than
ordinary class Echo airspace.
So we have to be 1,000
feet from the clouds here.
Here we just have to
be clear of the clouds.
Why are the minimums reduced
right around Logan Airport
and JFK and LAX than they are--
AUDIENCE: Because everyone's
in contact with the tower
so the tower knows
where everyone is.
PHILIP GREENSPUN:
Yeah, great answer.
So her answer is that
air traffic control
is in contact with everybody
in class Bravo airspace
and knows where they are.
And in fact, they're
on clearances
in class Bravo airspace, so
they're being told what to do.
Fly this heading.
Fly that heading.
Maintain this altitude.
Great answer.
All right, so how do we know
if the weather minimums are
going to be maintained?
Let's talk about weather theory.
So raise your hand if
you're a science major here
as opposed to engineering?
Where are the smart scientists?
All right, Francis.
So the science
approach to this task
would be to say if we could just
assume that humans are only 4
inches tall, then we could build
some really great aircraft.
And we'll get into
that in a moment.
Just think about that.
If you're a scientist,
how much flexibility
can you have compared
to being an engineer?
All right, so let's look at
the atmosphere that we do have.
Mostly, the troposphere
tops out around 40,000 feet
according to this chart.
And that's where most
of the water vapor
is and, therefore, most
of the weather, also
the higher temperatures.
You can see it actually does
get warm again way up high
in the thermosphere.
This is in kilometers
on the left.
So you can see that part of the
earth that we're flying through
is really just, I don't know,
probably around 20 kilometers
and down.
What did I say?
Said he could go up to
65,000 feet in this F-22.
So that's what?
That's a little over 10 miles.
Yeah, it's about 20 kilometers,
somewhere in that neighborhood.
Anyway, so not too many
people are going higher
than just the bottom 0
through 20 on this chart.
All right, who's concerned
about global inequality?
Raise your hand.
Awesome.
Well, you'll be pleased to
know that so is the FAA.
And this figure here shows you
why it's warmer at the equator
than up at the North Pole.
There's the same amount--
we're missing a little bit
of tilt here, but that's OK.
There's the same amount of
incoming solar radiation,
but it gets spread out over
a larger portion of the earth
up near the poles.
All right, so this is where
guys like Francis have it easy.
If you want to
understand something,
you just say, well, you
know, I've got an earth,
and it's pretty much the
same as the existing earth.
It just doesn't have
any water on it.
And it doesn't
rotate, and it's not
tilted with respect to the sun.
So now I'll do my analysis.
And I'll publish my paper.
And I'll get tenure, and
your problem is solved.
Let's see.
What would happen here?
In a non-rotating,
non-tilted waterless earth,
it would get hotter
at the equator,
and the air would
rise up from the heat.
So we can see that here.
So we would have low pressure
right there at the equator.
And then the air
would circulate up,
and we would have high
pressure up at the polls.
Does that makes
sense to everybody?
All right, great,
problem solved.
We can go home.
Unfortunately, as
engineers, we have
to deal with the real
world a little bit more.
So if we're spinning
around the Earth,
We're going to end up
with these three cells
and in each hemisphere.
And in this case,
you end up still
with a low pressure
at the equator.
But then you get a high pressure
with all the air sinking down
here.
And you get still low pressure--
you still get high pressure up
at the polls and low pressure
down here.
See if I got that right.
High.
I should be high.
It says high pressure
at 30 degrees North.
Oh yeah, high,
high, that's good.
And, yes, and low and low.
All right, we got that right.
It gets more
confusing as you see.
OK, so the
circulation-- one thing
that the FAA wants
you to know is
that it's heat exchange
that drives the weather.
So the weather is basically a
function of the sun heating up
the earth.
And then it's not
uniform, so the heat
gets pushed from one part
of the earth to another.
And all of this
unequal heating is
responsible for the
altimeter varying,
for wind blowing around.
Pretty much every phenomenon
that is of interest to pilots
is caused by heat trying
to move from the hotter
parts of the earth to the
colder parts of the earth.
We'll talk a little
bit more about these.
But notice there's
parts of the earth
that are windier than others.
Unfortunately, we're in
one of the windier parts.
OK, so you also have to know as
a pilot just what an isobar is.
That's a line of equal pressure.
And that tells you--
that gives you an idea of how
the wind is going to move.
We'll see that in a minute.
The tighter the isobars,
the more dramatic
the pressure change in a region.
And it's the pressure
gradient force
that's causing the wind
to flow from the high
to the low pressure.
So you might think
on this chart,
for example, that wherever
you see an L and an H
that you would just draw a
vector of wind from one place
to the other, right?
That kind of makes sense.
However, there is
Coriolis force.
This is for Francis,
the science major.
Francis, what course are you?
AUDIENCE: I'm course
9, so [INAUDIBLE]..
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Oh.
All right, so scientists
wear lab coats.
[LAUGHTER]
Coriolis force is a fake
news force formerly known
as fictitious.
So you can see they're
throwing the ball straight.
But because they're on
a rotating platform,
it's apparently curving.
So camera is mounted
to the ground,
and we'll see the
ball going straight.
They're going to draw you a
little dash line at one point
so you can see the path
is actually straight.
So the ball has an inertia.
Basically, once
it's launched, it
wants to keep doing
whatever it was doing.
And this guy's white
lab coated colleague
just moves away from
where the ball was going.
Whoa.
All right, everybody's got that?
That's Coriolis force for you.
What happens when we
do this on the earth?
So think about it.
You have a parcel
of air that's moving
with the earth at the equator.
If you displace it up
to a higher latitude,
it still has that velocity.
But now the Earth
isn't spinning as fast.
So it ends up essentially moving
a little bit to the right.
That is the fundamental insight
just as you saw in that video.
You'll have to go home and
think about that a little bit.
But, basically, I think
the most effective way
to think about it is just
that a parcel of air that
was the equator wants to keep
moving as if it were still
at the equator, but
it's not there anymore,
so it moves relative to
the underlying earth.
If you combine the Coriolis
force and the pressure
gradient, then you get
the actual wind direction.
And the trend as seen here--
eventually, there's
so much Coriolis force
over so much time
that the wind actually
moves exactly 90 degrees to
where you think it should move.
It flows along the isobars
instead of perpendicular
across them.
So there you have a
couple pressure systems
and you see that the wind is
circulating around these lows
and highs rather than flowing
directly from one to the other
as you'd expect.
All right, who would like to
become a helicopter test pilot?
Raise your hand if that
sounds like a fun job.
OK, so when you're developing
the manual for your Sikorsky
helicopter, you've
got to go somewhere
where the wind is calm.
Where would you all
suggest going now
that you've seen this chart?
What's your name, sir?
Sorry.
AUDIENCE: Jeremy.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Jeremy,
where do you want to go?
You're going to take
your Sikorsky helicopter
and you're going
to write the POH.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] Florida.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Florida.
Sikorsky, which is
headquartered in Connecticut,
they have a big
flight test facility.
I believe it's in Palm Beach.
So there you have it.
They thought just along
the same lines as you,
and they'll be in
the horse latitudes.
There's a whole bunch of--
nobody really knows why it's
called the horse latitudes.
One idea is that the ships--
since there's no wind
in those latitudes,
they have to find a
current, and then they
get pulled along by the current
as if they were on a horse.
All right, surface friction
is a little bit complicated.
It tends to drag down the wind.
You'll have to study this
vector diagram on your own.
But, really, from the
FAA's point of view,
they just want
you to know mostly
that the wind 2,000
or 3,000 feet up is
going to be different from
the wind on the surface.
Because of surface
friction, it will
be less intense and in a
slightly different direction.
OK, vertical
circulation of the air.
I think you're going to be OK
if you just remember that warmer
air is lighter than colder air.
That's all that you
pretty much need to know.
OK, local wind patterns.
If you heat up the shore line,
the air will rise off the shore
and pull in air from the
ocean during the daytime
so you get that sea breeze.
And then at nighttime,
the opposite happens,
so you get a land breeze.
So there are some of these
predictable local weather
patterns.
The bigger ones have to do
with atmospheric stability.
If you have a stable
atmosphere, meaning
that a displaced parcel of air
tends to get pushed back down
to wherever it was, then you get
these weather characteristics
where you're not going to be
bumped around in your aircraft.
You're going to
have trouble seeing,
and you're going to see clouds
that are basically flat,
these stratiform clouds here
that you see on the right.
If it rains, it's just
going to rain all day.
It's going to be a typical
miserable New England
day where it rains all the
time, or Seattle, I guess,
is like that as well.
Well, what about if
the air once displaced
tends to want to
keep being displaced?
If it rises up a little
bit, it keeps rising.
Then you have these clouds
with vertical development.
And the good news is
you can see really well.
You're not going to have an
obstruction to visibility
unless you're in heavy rain.
And the rain won't be
all day, every day.
It'll be showery, but
it'll be very turbulent
if you get into that
cloud or maybe right
underneath that cloud.
OK, what about the
profile of the atmosphere?
Let's have a look at this.
So on the right--
I wonder if this is
actually my newest
version of the presentation.
We'll see.
I corrected an error.
On the right, you can see that
for every 1,000 feet you go up.
So we go from 0
to 1,000 feet up.
The temperature is gone
from 18 Celsius to 15,
so it's lapsed by 3 degrees.
And the dew point has gone
down by half a degree.
Does that makes sense?
The air goes up,
it's lower pressure.
This is called an
adiabatic process.
I was not a chemistry
major, but I
think that means that we're
not adding or taking away
heat from the air.
We're just moving it.
So the temperature
and dew point spread,
actually does get narrower.
You can see as we rise up to
5,000 feet that the spread has
gone down to 2 and 1/2 degrees
because the dew point is not
falling nearly as fast as
the overall temperature.
Does that make sense?
So I think this conceivably
could be an FAA test
question that the dry adiabatic
lapse rate is 3 degrees.
OK, then the moist air is
lapsing only at 2 degrees.
So this figure shows you
going from 0 to 1,000 feet,
and from 1 to 2,000
feet, we were dropping
3 degrees per thousand feet.
After that, we're dropping only
2 degrees per thousand feet.
And once the temperature
dew point spread goes to 0,
that's when a cloud happens.
So the air can't hold
anymore water vapor.
And when the temperature
and dew point meet,
the water vapor
turns into water,
and now you've got a cloud.
All right, so you might
ask yourself, well,
why is this air moving at all?
Why does it start moving?
One thing that can start it
moving is a mountain range.
So the air gets pushed
by a wind coming
from the left side of the slide
up the top of the mountain.
And at that point, it will
condense into a cloud.
Just let you absorb that
cloud here for a minute.
Notice also that
relative humidity is just
another way of stating the
temperature dew point spread.
So here temperature and
dew point are pretty close,
10 and 15 or 15 and 10.
So we've got relative
humidity of 80%.
Over here, they're
quite far apart.
The temperature is 23, and
the dew point is minus 2.
So the relative humidity is low.
OK, you've heard that there's
a cold front coming in
and we have all
these thunderstorms.
Well, this is why.
The cold air is denser
than the warm air.
So it pushes the warm air up.
And at that point, you
get clouds forming,
and you get thunderstorms
all along the line
of the cold front.
OK, so what if you
have stable air?
Let's have a look at this.
You end up--
Let's see.
We've gone from 0, to
1, to 2, and we're only
dropping-- actually,
we're not dropping at all.
And then we're back up.
This is an inversion.
OK, so, basically,
the air temperature
is pretty constant as we go up.
So if a parcel of air rises
up into the atmosphere,
it's not going to be warmer
than the surrounding air,
so it doesn't want
to keep rising.
OK, what if it's unstable?
So look at this by contrast.
The environmental
air temperature
is lapsing at a higher
than standard rate.
It's going down 4 degrees
Celsius per thousand feet.
And this parcel of air
that was in equilibrium
down at sea level is still
warmer than the surrounding
air, and, therefore, it
wants to keep rising.
Does that make sense?
So, basically, if it goes up
and it wants to keep going up,
that's unstable and
a perfect situation
for forming thunderstorms,
which we'll talk about shortly.
Temperature inversion like
we saw on that earlier slide
where it was actually a
little bit warmer here,
that tends to keep
air where it is,
and, therefore, you end
up with poor visibility
and haze because
all the stuff that's
obscuring your visibility
is just staying
underneath the inversion.
It's kind of a
common phenomenon I
think in some of these
basins like Los Angeles.
Talk about an inversion,
and ordinary people
think about that, and hear
that term, and worry about it.
Most frequently-- you're going
to I think see this on a test
maybe--
is phenomena having to do with
the ground radiating back heat
into the atmosphere or
into space at night.
Tends to make the
ground cold and the air
right next to the ground cold,
whereas the air just slightly
higher than that, a
couple thousand feet up,
hasn't changed the
temperature too much.
So the terrestrial radiation
on a clear still night
can cause a
temperature inversion.
We talked about this earlier
when the temperature and dew
point meet, and that's when
the water vapor will condense.
Frost.
When the dew point
is below freezing
and you have a surface that's
cold, then you will get--
maybe it's cold because
it radiated its heat
back out into space
at night, for example.
That's when you
get frost forming.
And you want to definitely
clear that off your aircraft
before you go anywhere
because it messes
with the smooth flow of the air,
so the wing becomes much less
efficient even if the shape
hasn't changed that much.
All right, let's look
at the kinds of clouds.
You've got basically--
the prefix to the cloud
tells you what height it is.
And then the second
part of the word
tells you kind of the
shape of the cloud.
So I'll just let you
absorb this a little bit.
If it says nimbo, yeah,
cumulonimbus or nimbostratus,
that means it's raining.
Towering cumulus is bad
if they talk about that.
And cumulonimbus is the worst.
That's just another fancier
way of saying thunderstorm.
OK, so here's your
Latin lesson for today.
Unfortunately, I
didn't study Latin.
It would have been
nice when I went
to Peru to be able
to communicate
with the locals
in Latin America.
OK, that wasn't funny I guess.
[LAUGHTER]
If you have low clouds, the
main hazard to worry about
is the icing.
If the water is supercooled,
that's the worst.
You can usually get
a forecast of that.
You'll get AIRMETs
for icing, and they
might talk about supercooled
water is a hazard.
I guess this might
be an exam question.
Stratus clouds form when moist,
stable air flows upslope.
But just remember stable
usually means the flat clouds,
stratiform clouds.
And unstable is where you
get the cumuliform clouds.
So same deal.
Those altocumulus
are going to be
much more turbulent and probably
more severe icing potential.
The high clouds-- it's so
cold in the high atmosphere
that the maximum amount of
water that can be stored
is pretty low,
and, therefore, you
don't tend to get
ice when it's below
say minus 15 degrees Celsius.
There just isn't a whole lot
of moisture to begin with.
OK, so this is
what as a GA pilot
you're more likely to
have to worry about.
You're probably not going
to be up at 25,000 feet
in your Piper Warrior.
But you could be
underneath a cumulus cloud.
I will tell you that
if you have passengers
and there is low cumulus
clouds, you desperately
want to get above those.
So let's say there's a bunch
of cumulus clouds at 4,000
or 5,000 feet.
You can climb probably
to 8,000 or 10,000 feet
in a light airplane, and
that'll be much, much smoother.
So as soon as you get
above the cumulus clouds,
that's where the air
tends to smooth out,
and it'll be much
more comfortable.
But if it's a towering
cumulus cloud,
they may go up to as high as
60,000 feet down in Texas.
And you really
can't get over them
in anything short of an
SR-71 or maybe last as F-22.
Even the latest Gulfstreams
only go to 51,000, I believe.
OK, so thunderstorms
are the worst hazard.
Even the airliners get in
trouble and thunderstorms
with hail smashing into the
windshield and turbulence that
can bend stuff.
So how do you predict
if you're flying along--
well, if you're preparing
to go on a flight,
how do you predict where
the clouds are likely to be?
One thing you do is look at the
temperature dew point spread.
The FAA tells you to use a lapse
rate of 2.5 degrees Celsius
to figure out where
the clouds will be.
So if there is a 10 degree
temperature dew point spread,
then you should expect
the clouds to have
a base at about 4,000 feet.
There's a typo in the slide.
Sorry about that.
I thought we had the new
version in the Dropbox.
The temperature lapses at 3
for the dry adiabatic air.
You remember that?
And the dew point's at 0.5.
So if we go back
to that figure--
I think it was our-- yeah.
Yeah, if we go back
here, you remember this?
We went from 18, to 15, to 12.
And the dew point, meanwhile,
is falling from 3, to 2 and 1/2,
to 2.
So that's why.
It's 2.5 as a rule of thumb.
That's not great, but
you can actually--
Just look at METARs
around the country,
and I think you will see
because they give you
the basis of the clouds
and the ceilings.
I think you usually
will see that it's
reasonably close to this formula
but almost never spot on.
OK, this is worth studying.
I'm not going to cover
it completely here.
But some of these
are exam questions.
Advection fog-- I
think I remember
they like to ask about that,
when the warm moist air moves
over a cool surface
along coastlines.
So I think that makes sense.
Maybe that's what they're
having in California
a lot of the time.
They have the fog over
the coastal areas.
And radiation fog-- also,
in the Western deserts,
oftentimes, there's
fog in the morning.
So I think you're advection fog
would be a coastal phenomenon.
And the radiation
fog, something they
can have in a place like
Arizona or Palm Springs.
OK, the FAA loves this.
If you see ice pellets, you
probably shouldn't be flying.
But they want you to know that
if you do see ice pellets,
how did they arrive?
Well, they had to be
freezing rain up higher.
So don't climb in hopes
of getting out of the ice
pellets because then you'll have
freezing rain on your airplane
which is probably the worst
kind of icing-related hazard.
OK, airmasses.
You can just have a look here.
If you hear that there's
a polar airmass coming in,
it's going to be cold,
not too exciting.
Might be a question.
Fronts, they do
want you to see--
be able to read
one of these maps.
They may occasionally
asked you a question.
So one thing to remember
is the cold front
has the pointy
spikes like icicles.
So if you can remember
that, you'll be pretty good.
There's a cold front.
Again, you can just read this
and study it at your leisure.
I guess they might
want you to remember
that the front is the boundary
between two air masses.
OK.
Here's a typical
drawing where they'll
show you the cold fronts
and the warm fronts.
When there is a
front, how do you
know when the front
has gone through?
Well, the temperature's
changed and the wind's changed,
simple as that.
Here's a little explanation
of what you can expect
when a cold front goes through.
Everybody is happy with that?
OK.
When a warm front goes through,
it gets warmer afterwards.
Yeah, so the warm front
produces, as you can see,
light to moderate rain,
drizzle, visibility is bad.
That's actually the
important thing here.
The visibility gets poor.
And then it becomes
fair and haze,
whereas the visibility becomes
really good after a cold front
comes through.
Occluded fronts-- same
deal, bad visibility.
All right.
Let's talk about hazards.
This is more important.
So this is a summary
of where heat
is released into the atmosphere
versus absorbed by water.
So as the water goes, for
example, from vapor to liquid,
it releases heat.
So that's exactly
what's happening when
it's raining in a thunderstorm.
And that's not a good thing.
All right.
So here's the FAA's chart
of a cumulus cloud forming.
So you can see the
lapse rate over here
in the ambient atmosphere.
It's going from 28
to 24 down to 21.
So it is, at least
initially, higher
than standard lapse rate.
So this warm air--
it starts at 28.
And then it drops only to 25.
So it's still warmer
than the surrounding air.
So it goes into becoming
this big, nasty cloud.
There's this-- you
can see-- if you don't
want to look at the summaries
of weather forecasts,
you can look at these
shards of lifted index.
Here, it shows the difference
between minus 18 and minus 11,
minus 7.
That gives you a measure of
the thunderstorm potential.
There are charts of that.
But as pilots, this
is more what we
deal with on our practical
day-to-day basis.
We just look at
the next rad data
from the radar stations that
are strewn around the country.
And if it's red, we try
to find a path around it,
because there's just
not much else you
can do in a little aircraft.
It's possible that you could
get over this entire front
if you were in a jet
that could climb up
to 40,000 feet or higher.
But in a Piper or
Cessna or Cirrus,
you're just not going
to be able to do that.
OK.
The thunderstorm lifecycle--
this is, I think,
my favorite test question.
How do you know that
the thunderstorm
has reached its mature stage?
Well, it's raining,
simple as that.
If it's raining, it's mature.
If it's dissipating, you're
going to get these downdrafts.
If it's building,
you get updrafts.
So everything comes up,
and then it all comes down.
OK.
Look at that nasty thunderstorm.
You're going to get
turbulence right on top of it.
If you can clear that
thunderstorm by 5,000 feet,
it'll probably nice and smooth.
So this is your good argument
for a plane that can go to 51
[INAUDIBLE] or 510.
Airliners don't go that high.
The latest these jets go
much higher than airliners.
All right.
The hazard-- we're
going to hear more
about this tomorrow
from [? Dojo, ?]
from the Brazilian Air Force.
But there is this chart here
that shows you how much load
factor-- that's in g's.
If you're going pretty
fast, you can pretty quickly
get into the structural
damage range.
So that's why they tell you--
this these lines here are
basically--
this is how many g's you
can get on the aircraft
with either extreme
movements on the controls
or extreme movements
that are imposed on you
by a thunderstorm or something.
So the takeaway
from this diagram
is slow down if you get
into heavy turbulence,
because then the airplane
will stall before it bends.
And stalling can be corrected
by pushing the nose down.
OK.
So these are all of the
hazards from thunderstorms.
Again, it's a lot better--
in this day and age,
there's so much information
out there and datalink
available in the cockpit
that going through thunderstorms
is just much less common
than it used to be.
And therefore, don't really
have to remember too much, other
than don't fly through
a thunderstorm.
Microburst-- however, if
you're trying to land and beat
the thunderstorm,
you can actually
get into a little
bit of trouble,
because the wind right before
a thunderstorm or right
after can be pretty squirrelly
and cause you some difficulties
here.
Let's see.
What do we have?
So here, this airplane is
getting a performance boost
from a strong headwind.
Now, not much is
happening, except that it's
getting pushed down, maybe
faster than the airplane can
climb.
And at this point, you're
getting a performance reduction
from this big tailwind.
So that's reducing-- you might
think, well, that's great.
I'm getting pushed
along with a tailwind.
But if it's suddenly
taking away your airspeed,
then that's not a
performance boost.
All right.
So the thunderstorm
emergency procedures
are, again, probably
a little bit
less relevant now
that we're living
in this world of constant
datalink and NEXRAD data.
2006, there was a famous
accident with a former test
pilot, Scott
Crossfield, who maybe
didn't get the best advice
from air traffic control.
And I don't think he had
datalink in his cockpit.
The Boeing B 29 bomber
crews, they would fly,
I think, seven or eight hours
from an island in the Pacific
over to Japan.
And during those
eight hours, they
had satellite data, no
data from a ground station.
So they just had no idea
what they were going through.
And they didn't go as high
as the designers thought
that airplane was designed
to go, super high.
But they were so loaded
up with fuel and bombs,
they couldn't practically
climb all that high.
So they were going at
10-15,000 feet over the ocean.
And at those altitudes,
you can't really see--
you may get into an
embedded thunderstorm.
Today's airliners, they go so
high that you really are never
in a position where
you blunder into stuff,
or almost never, because
you're in the clear,
and you can just see
the towering cumulus
and not fly there.
You just back
yourself around them.
So I guess-- yeah,
the final statement
there is, get-there-itis
hasn't been cured.
So as a pilot, the
safest thing you can do
is really fight that
tendency to want
to complete the
mission as planned
and overcommit to
your plan of action.
All right.
There are three other categories
of turbulence to worry about.
Probably the worst is due
to terrain, like mountains.
This low level turbulence
from thermals is not crazy.
But as I said, if you get above
the clouds, that plane on top
is going to be in
a nice, smooth air.
Wake turbulence [INAUDIBLE] is
also another thing to consider.
Let's look at that.
So if you're taking off behind
an airplane, so look at that--
heavy, slow and in
clean configuration.
So airplanes will tend
to retract their flaps,
and therefore be in
a clean configuration
shortly after takeoff,
whereas, if they're landing,
the flaps are down.
They're not generating quite
as much wake turbulence.
Although, still if you land
behind a Boeing, in your little
Cessna, you will notice that.
The solution here--
and I think this
is a test question--
is you land or take off
beyond the touchdown
point of a large aircraft.
So if the large aircraft--
let's say the large aircraft
landed right here in front
of the laptop on the runway.
You just fly a
little bit higher.
And you land maybe in
the middle of the runway.
And that way, you can't possibly
get into wake turbulence,
because it will have sunk below
that big aircraft's flight
path.
Controllers at a
towered airport,
they'll also separate you by
the necessary number of minutes.
They have a bunch of regulations
about how much separation
they have to have
between aircraft.
And then similarly,
for liftoff point--
so if the big airplane--
again, this is not really that
much of a practical problem,
because so little runway
is used by light airplanes.
But if the big airplane rotated
and took off and started
climbing here, well,
then you take off
and start climbing earlier.
Of course, the climb
rate of the big airplane
is probably a lot
better than you are.
So you've got to think about
which way the wind is going
and maybe try to
turn away from it.
I've only really been
stuck in weight turbulence
once that I can think about.
It was at Hanscom Field.
And there was a
heavy helicopter that
was cleared to
land on the runway,
and then transitioned sideways.
And I was in the Cirrus.
And I think the
controllers didn't really
think about, well, how
much wake turbulence can
a helicopter generate.
So I was trying to land.
And maybe about 200
feet above the ground,
there was a sharp
wing dip that I--
the good news is you don't have
to be heroic to correct it,
because, if your
airplane is banked,
the natural tendency is to
want to take the bank out.
So whenever your
natural tendency
is to do the safe thing, that's
usually not much of a problem.
Oh yeah.
So anyway, here's
the FAA question.
Who wants to give an answer?
Shout it out.
A, B, or C?
AUDIENCE: A.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yay.
All right.
So this is a practical
issue, especially for anybody
who wants to fly out west.
You have the Sierra Mountains.
You have the Rocky Mountains.
And you have to be very careful
when crossing these mountain
ranges.
If the wind aloft forecast
is more than about 30 knots
for the time that you're
planning on crossing,
you can expect this kind of
turbulence on the lee side
or the eastern side of
those mountain ranges.
So when I've crossed those
mountains in light airplanes,
I have usually done it first
thing in the morning basically.
So I arranged to shut down
just short of the mountains
the night before, and then
cross early in the morning
when the winds are
typically calm.
So you can look for
these lenticular clouds.
But again, if you
saw the winds aloft
forecast that it was going to
be blowing 50 knots at 12,000
feet, you can be
pretty sure that it's
going to be turbulent.
All right.
Structural icing-- you can
get rime, clear or mixed.
I'll just let you look
through the conditions that
lead to this.
Clearing rime-- probably
rime icing is more common.
What happens?
Everything gets worse
about your aircraft.
Especially if
you're on autopilot,
it's a challenge to recognize
when icing is occurring.
You can be in the air,
fat, dumb, and happy
while the airplane gets iced up.
So the worst part of it, I
guess, is that you can't climb.
Basically, when your airplane
has all this performance
reduction, you can
summarize this all--
if it's only moderate
icing, basically you
have an aircraft
that can't climb.
All you can do is descend.
So a good practical tip is, if
you're-- well, first off all,
the good news is, if
you're a VFR pilot,
like you guys are
going to become,
initially you shouldn't
have to worry about icing,
because it's a phenomenon that
occurs when you're in a cloud.
So you shouldn't be in a
cloud if you're a VFR pilot
to begin with.
So how did you get ice?
The exception might be
freezing rain, if you somehow
drive through freezing rain.
But if you are instrument-rated
and you are going somewhere--
I'm planning on going to New
York next week in the Cirrus.
So if it's cloudy, even if
there's no icing forecast,
I know that there is a risk
of getting ice on the wings.
So in the wintertime,
I just say,
well look, I'm not going to
go unless it's above freezing
on the surface, because,
if I get iced up,
then inadvertently I
need an escape route.
And if it's going to be above
freezing at, say, 3,000 feet,
well, that's fine.
I know that I probably
won't be able to climb
if I get moderate icing, but
I will be able to descend.
Even a brick can descend.
So descend down to 3,000 feet,
and all the ice will melt off.
That would be great.
But if it's below
freezing on the surface,
then it's basically a no-go.
I've definitely had
icing a few times.
And it's pretty scary.
I was out on a day when
with an instrument student.
And it seemed like
a perfect day to go
practice instrument flying.
There was no turbulence.
There was just
clouds everywhere,
about 800 feet of ceiling.
So you could be in the
clouds, do real approaches,
get experience with actual IMC.
And halfway through
the flight, I
started criticizing this guy
for using way too much power.
The power settings were all off.
What are you doing wrong?
And then I looked
out on the wings.
And I saw they were all frosted.
So we descended.
We managed to complete an
ILS approach into Lawrence
and pulled the airplane
into a warm hangar
and got it warmed up.
So actually, as we
were as we were flying,
the FAA issued an
AIRMET for icing,
but the controllers
never told us about it.
All right.
Requirements for
icing formation--
near freezing temperatures,
minus 10 to 0, is the worst.
You have to have a surface
on which the ice can form.
And you have to be invisible
moisture, basically.
So again, if you're flying in
the clear with your VFR pilot
certificate, icing should
not be a factor for you.
Yeah.
So as I said below, go
through a cold cloud
only if you have an escape
route of warm air below.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] for
the engine [INAUDIBLE]
as far as getting the icing
in the carburetor [INAUDIBLE]..
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yeah.
So the question is, what
about icing in the engine?
So you can get carb ice
that we talked about.
You can get carb ice when
it's 50 degrees outside,
as long as it's humid.
So it's slightly unrelated.
The main problem with
engines is that you
can get ice in the induction.
So if the intake for the engine
where it's trying to breathe
gets iced over, then there's
an alternate-- again,
they're relying
on the hero pilot.
Some airplanes actually,
it'll just open automatically,
the vacuum of trying to suck the
air through the intake that's
not working will cause
some backup door to open.
And a lot of--
most IFR-certified aircraft have
an alternate air lever that you
can pull and have air pulled
from somewhere inside the--
it's a little more protected
inside the airframe.
Does that answer your question?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So I guess you're saying as
long as the heat's working
your [INAUDIBLE].
PHILIP GREENSPUN: As
long as which heat?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
PHILIP GREENSPUN:
You're not going
to get carb icing and airframe
icing at the same time
probably.
I think, at that point,
it's probably too cold.
I'm not I'm not sure.
Well, the other issue is
you're probably not going
to fly a carburated
airplane into the clouds,
because the real IFR airplanes
that people use to travel,
like Cirruses and
Bonanzas and stuff,
in challenging conditions, those
are almost all fuel injected.
But you do have to worry about
induction icing, like I said.
OK.
Icing layers are
usually pretty thin.
So if you're in a jet, you
just add power and climb up
another few thousand feet
and you're out of it.
Again, one of the
effects of icing
is to dramatically reduce
your climb performance.
So this best approach
of climbing out of it
is not always available.
You will end up using more
power on the final approach.
And you'll add speed as
well, because the stall
speed may have gone up.
And you can't really be
sure, since it hasn't
been quantified and tested.
You probably won't use flaps.
And you'll not
make severe turns.
So there's a good NASA video
that I encourage you to watch,
especially as you work on higher
performance aircraft and IFR.
NASA has this great
video about icing.
OK.
How do the transportation
class airplanes handle this?
One approach is to push
antifreeze out onto the wings.
That used to be called TKS.
Now, it's called CAV.
It's just a brand name.
So if you go to a flight school
and you see a modern Cirrus,
like the SR22s, the
leading edges of the wings
will be metal.
And they'll have little
tiny holes in them.
And that's for this
antifreeze to come out.
If you have a very light
jet or a turbo prop,
you may have rubber boots on the
wings and on the tail surfaces.
And those inflate to
crack the ice off.
The jets are really
the ultimate--
the bigger jets
all have bleed air.
Remember, the jets
are compressing
air so much that it becomes
really hot even before it's
burned.
So you pull the bleed
air off the compressor,
and you run it out into the
leading edges of the wings.
And that just melts the ice off.
The transporter aircraft, they
also heat the windshields.
So you'll be able
to see when you do--
if it's not above
freezing at the airport,
you'll have a clear windshield,
so you can leave the runway.
Even in very basic
airplanes like a Cirrus,
if they're IFR-certified,
the pedo tube
is going to be heated.
There will be pedo heat.
OK.
You can learn a whole
bunch more about this.
I think everything
you know to pass
the test is pretty much
in the Pilot's Handbook
of Aeronautical Knowledge.
There's a little bit in the AIM.
If you want to dig deeper
and understand more of it,
then I would encourage you
to look at these FAA weather
publications.
One is about weather theory
and one is about information
that you can get
from various sources.
There's also these videos that I
would encourage you to look at.
One of them is called
"Ambushed by Ice"
and "Into Deep--"
these particular links,
don't write those down, because
I fixed them last night,
but the Dropbox
didn't update yet.
Do they have real-time
weather data?
So the question is, in your
basic trainer airplane,
do they have real-time
weather data?
So let's just talk about
East Coast Aero Club
is a typical higher
end flight school.
About maybe 10 years ago,
almost all the aircraft
had a Garmin IFR-certified
GPS put in, a Garmin 430.
So at that point, you
had a really good GPS.
But they did not have XM weather
pulling data from satellites,
which we'll talk
about in a little bit,
because it's a $500 a year
subscription and a $10,000 box.
So people didn't want to do it.
With ADS-B, the FAA is now
providing some of the same data
that XM was providing
for free, as long
as you have an ADS-B
in transponder.
And the East Coast
Aero-- well, everybody
has to upgrade to ADS-B by 2020.
Not everybody has
to have ADS-B in,
but I think East Coast
Aero Club's probably
fairly typical of the
better flight schools.
They've put-- or they're
gradually putting in a ADS-B
in and out transponders
in all their aircraft.
It won't display in the cockpit.
You'll have to have your
phone, your iPad, or something.
But you'll be able to see--
you'll be able to see
NEXRAD radar picture.
You'll be able to
get METARs and TAFs.
You'll get all of that.
So I think--
TINA: But if you don't want
to rely on someone else--
this is MIT.
You can actually get
that data yourself.
So when we talk about
weather data today,
we're going to
also talk about how
you can do it yourself,
build your own Stratux ADS-B
receiver.
And I've actually done this.
It was really fun to do.
It's very easy, actually.
Basically, based on a Raspberry
Pi with a couple of antennas,
with a little cooling fan, you
can build a little box that
can receive that weather data.
And it actually-- the
software is open source.
And it can sync with
your other tools.
So I have it synced
with my Foreflight app.
So when I'm flying,
I plug that in, I
bring a backup battery for it.
And it gives me weather data
and some other traffic data.
And we'll be talking about
that in a couple hours.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yeah,
I should have noticed.
As Tina said, a lot of
flight school customers
for the last five years would
bring little battery powered
boxes and stick them to the
windshield of whatever they're
flying.
And they would get a whole
bunch of more modern services.
I personally don't love that.
When I started out
in my flying career,
I had my big flight
bag with all the stuff
I was going to bring
into the airplane.
And now, I have the
philosophy that I
don't want to bring
anything into the CIrrus
other than a pencil.
I want everything that I
need to be in the panel.
But yeah, I definitely think,
in the older airplanes,
it's become
conventional for people
to bring some sort of ADS-B
receiver and get that data.